Guide to the Records of the New York University College of Dentistry RG 25
New York University Archives
Records of the New York University College of Dentistry
circa 1550-2003
1850-1950
New York University Archives
RG 25
59.75 Linear Feet in 54 boxes
The New York College of Dentistry was founded in 1865 with thirty-one students and ten faculty members. In 1925, the College merged with New York University and developed into a leading center for dental care, research and policy. This collection allows the viewer to understand the School's development through a series of student notebooks and administrative files from the late 1800s and early 1900s. It also contains a wide array of antique dental tools and memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to the University Archives by the Waldman Library of the New York University College of Dentistry in August 2000; additional materials were transferred in December of 2015. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 80-011, 94-021, 03-006, 2016-002.
Arrangement
General administrative documents are filed by chronologically by subject. Student materials are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the student. Accreditation materials have not been arranged by an archivist.
The files are grouped into four series:
Series I: General Administration
Series II: Memorabilia
Series III: Student Records
Series IV: Accreditation Records
Historical Note
The New York College of Dentistry was established in 1865 in a small rental space on Twenty-Second Street and Fifth Avenue in Manhattan. The mission of the College was to promote altruism in dentistry while providing first-rate education. Upon its inception, the school had thirty-one students and ten faculty members. Only nine of the original thirty-one students graduated in the first graduating class.
When the New York College of Dentistry merged with New York University in 1925, it became known as the New York University College of Dentistry. The merger led to the creation of a dental school at the forefront of research and postdoctoral education.
Today, the College of Dentistry has approximately 1,600 students from across the world. About fifty percent of the student body is female, and fifty percent are minority students. The greater aim of the College is to improve the health of underserved populations, and more generally, to improve health worldwide.
The New York University College of Dentistry offers D.D.S., B.S. and A.A.S. degrees. It is now the third oldest and the largest private dental school in the United States.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes administrative and student records, memorabilia, and a large collection of dental tools and models.
Separated Materials
Promotional materials, bulletins, annual reports, publications, commencement records, audiovisual materials, and photographs were incorporated into the general University Archives collections for those formats.
Dentistry -- Study and teaching; Dental instruments and apparatus.; New York University. College of Dentistry
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Accreditation, Kriser Dental Center Waldmann Dental Library, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Act of Incorporation of NYCD, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement between NYU and NYCD, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alpha Omega Fraternity, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book of Contacts, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Centennial Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Centennial History, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clinical Fee Schedules, 1977, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clinic book, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clinics, 1889-1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dean's Memoranda, 1960-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dean Edward G. Kaufman Memoranda, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Department of Preventive Dentistry and Community Health, Dental Health Organizations, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Educational Standards, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Faculty, Lectures in Physiology, Professor Stein, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Faculty, Meeting Minutes, 1898-1915 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Faculty, Progress Examinations, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Faculty, Progress Examinations, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Faculty, Records, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Faculty, Records, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Faculty, Records, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty, Records, 1922-1923 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Faculty, Records, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Faculty, Records, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gifts/Donations, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Investigation into Theft, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Henry Dodge Record of Operations, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Henry Dodge Day Book, 1851-1852 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Murray and Leone Guggenheim Foundation for Dental Research, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Parent Agreement for Minors, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Parent Agreement for Minors, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Peridontia Corresponding Group, Bulletin 1- 25, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Registration, Applications, A-C, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Registration, Applications, D-Z, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Registration, Applications, A-Z, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1890-1891 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1892-1893 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1892-1893 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Student Record Book, 1898-1906 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Student Records, Non-attending Students, 1895-1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Student Records, Qualifying Certificates, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Student Records, Signature Book for Diplomas, 1897-1926 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Trustees and Directors, 1865-1897 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Trustees and Directors, 1904-1913 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Trustees and Directors, 1914-1925 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Trustees Roster, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Undergraduate Preventative Dentistry Variety Show, 1968-1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series II: Memorabilia
  - Medallions (10), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Paperweights (3), undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 19th Century Dental Tools (100+), 1800-1900 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Model teeth, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Small Metal Tools (10), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Moldings (2), undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Model Teeth (8), undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Model Teeth, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Tools (20), undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Film Reel, undated (Box 43)
  - Dental tool, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Provenance
    This item was given to Dr. Waldman by John Steinbeck.
  - Metal Plates (2), undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Plaques (6), undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Post Extractor, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Film, undated (Box 43)
  - Condyles (27), undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Pins (6), undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Gysi Trubyte Articulator, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Tools (28), undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Shells (5), undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Facebow, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Antique Instruments (25), undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
    These items were a gift from Erum Kaplan.
  - Stamps, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Atomizer, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Model Teeth, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Molten Metal Endo File, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Reame Sterilizer, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Paper Disks, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Protractor, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Cloth Strips, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Antique Dental Instruments (15), undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Plaques, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Saklad Nameplate, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Centennial Certificate, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Framed Faculty Photos (7), undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Benjamin R. Hoch Dental Toolkit with Tools, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - NYU Banners (2), undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Antique Dental Tools (20+) with Descriptions, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - X-rays (2), undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Records (3), undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Dr. J. Van Chandler Dental Toolkit with Tools, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Saklad Nameplate, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Framed Certificates (3), undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Antique Dental Toolkit and Tools, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - NYU College of Dentistry building illustration, circa 1940s (Box Shared University Archives 010)
  - Dentistry Alumni Banner, undated (Box 53)
- Series III: Student Records
  - College of Dentistry Admission Cards, 1889-1907 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, D-K, First Year Class, 1913-1914 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, A-Z, Third Year Class, 1913-1914 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Student Report Cards, Third Year Class, 1913-1914 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Student Report Cards, First Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Student Report Cards, A-H, Second Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Student Report Cards, H-P, Second Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, P-W, Second Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Student Report Cards, Third Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Student Report Cards, A-V, Third Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Student Report Cards, S-Z, Third Year Class, 1914-1915 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Student Report Cards, 1915-1916 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Student Report Cards, A-E, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Student Report Cards, E-K, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Student Report Cards, K-Z, 1926 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Student Report Cards, A-M, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Student Report Cards, M-P, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Student Report Cards, P-R, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Student Report Cards, M-R, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Student Report Cards, R-S, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Student Report Cards, S-W, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Student Report Cards, W-Z, 1927 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Student Report Cards, A-H, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Student Report Cards, H-P, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Student Report Cards, P-Z, 1928 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Student Report Cards, A-F, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Student Report Cards, G-L, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Student Report Cards, S-W, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - J.L. Blass Notebook, 1919 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - J.L. Blass Notebook, 1929 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - J.L. Blass Notebook, 1929 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Anesthesia, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Anatomy, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Chemical Lab, 1925 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Chemistry, Second and Third Year, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Diseases and General Surgery of the Mouth, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Student Lecture Notes, General Pathology, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Hypnosis, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Materia Medica, Second Year, undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Materia Medica, Third Year, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Operative Dentistry, undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Student Lecture Notes, George Kaplan, Oral Surgery, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Oral Case Recording, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Oral Case Recording, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Abraham Gralnick, Orthodontia, undated (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Orthodontia, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Physiology, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Physiology Lab, 1920 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Prosthetic Dentistry, Second and Third Year, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Jacob Louis Blass, 1929 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Student Lecture Notes, Jankelson, undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Student Lecture Notes, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Dental Student Qualifying Certificates: 1918 Graduates (Box 25, Item 1)
  - Dental Student Qualifying Certificates: 1919 Graduates (Box 25, Item 2)
  - Dental Student Qualifying Certificates: 1921 Graduates (Box 25, Item 3)
  - Dental Student Qualifying Certificates: 1922 Graduates (Box 25, Item 4)
  - Dental Student Qualifying Certificates: 1923 Graduates (Box 25, Item 5)
  - Dental Student Qualifying Certificates: 1924 Graduates (Box 25, Item 6)
  - Dental Student Qualifying Certificates: 1925 Graduates (Box 25, Item 7)
- Series IV. Accreditation Records, 1973-2003; 16.5 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials created through the course of a reaccreditation process that document various administrative and educational aspects of the College of Dentistry's programs. Materials include syllabi, information about the curriculum of the programs, reports outlining the programs' compliance with accreditation standards, and materials produced in preparation for accreditation site visits.
  - Predoctoral Curriculum, 1978-1989 (Box 25A, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 40, Box 41)
  - Self-Study Reaccreditation Reports, 1980, 1996, 2003 (Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34)
  - Standards for Accreditation, 1989 (Box 35, Box 36)
  - Syllabi, 1973-1975, 1989 (Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40)
  - Grants for Health Professions Schools, 1980 (Box 41)
  - Manual for Accreditation Site Visit, 1980 (Box 41)
  - Task Force Report, 1976 (Box 42)
  - Manuals for Accreditation, 1989 (Box 51)
- Unprocessed Materials (Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50)
  - Student Record Book, 1866-1906 (Box 54)